<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>agile on Seven steps</title>
    <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/tags/agile/</link>
    <description>Recent content in agile on Seven steps</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/trevoke&#34;&gt;Aldric Giacomoni&lt;/a&gt; 2017-2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 10:26:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.trevoke.net/tags/agile/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Agile and lean art delivery</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/agile-and-lean-art-delivery/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 10:26:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/agile-and-lean-art-delivery/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve been helping teams and organizations improve their approach to agile and lean delivery for a decade now, and by far one of the most difficult things to wrap one&amp;#39;s head around is the idea of iterative delivery of value. I don&amp;#39;t know about you, but I&amp;#39;m tired of these various hypothetical images depicting what agile delivery is supposed to look like. Is it a skateboard that becomes a car?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slack time explained</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/slack-time-explained/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 18:10:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/slack-time-explained/</guid>
      <description>What problem are we trying to solve?   You&amp;#39;re a software product team. Your job is to steadily deliver working product. Generally this means there&amp;#39;s two types of work you&amp;#39;re going to do:    Work that directly correlates to delivering value to the customer    Work that directly correlates to the ability to keep on delivering value at the same pace    In &amp;#34;agile&amp;#34; terminology, those categories are labeled, respectively, &amp;#34;stories&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;tech debt&amp;#34;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The value of estimates for a team</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/the-value-of-estimates-for-a-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/the-value-of-estimates-for-a-team/</guid>
      <description>What this entry is and is not about   This entry talks about estimates in a relatively perfect world. This entry does not talk about problems that teams run into when dealing with estimates in a world where estimates are often misunderstood and where parties try to pile up additional meanings and metrics to estimates. Why talk about estimating at all   Estimating work to be done before it is done.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art of Agile Planning / Art of Agile Delivery, by James Shore and Diana Larsen</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-art-of-agile-planning-art-of-agile-delivery-by-james-shore-and-diana-larsen-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-art-of-agile-planning-art-of-agile-delivery-by-james-shore-and-diana-larsen-publish/</guid>
      <description>The Art of Agile Planning (#aoap on Twitter, and AOAP from now on) is a 2-day course. The focus is on understanding the higher-level constructs of Agile and how they imbricate. In the course, one learns how the ideal Agile team is composed (hint: it&amp;#39;s cross-functional and co-located) and what practices and techniques will be used to organize at all levels, from the developers&amp;#39; standup to the customers&amp;#39; research for the next best value-delivering feature, including how to properly create a feature that developers can work on and how to best break it down into stories (and then into tasks).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>