<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philosophy on Seven steps</title>
    <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/categories/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philosophy on Seven steps</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/trevoke&#34;&gt;Aldric Giacomoni&lt;/a&gt; 2017-2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.trevoke.net/categories/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning and fear</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-learning-and-fear-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-learning-and-fear-publish/</guid>
      <description>“Life is going to present to you a series of transformations. And the point of education should be to transform you. To teach you how to be transformed so you can ride the waves as they come. But today, the point of education is not education. It’s accreditation. The more accreditation you have, the more money you make. That’s the instrumental logic of neoliberalism. And this instrumental logic comes wrapped in an envelope of fear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Litany Against Fear</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-the-litany-against-fear-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-the-litany-against-fear-publish/</guid>
      <description>So, the litany against fear goes like this:
&amp;nbsp; I must not fear. Fear is the mind-killer. Fear is the little-death that brings total obliteration. I will face my fear. I will permit it to pass over me and through me. And when it has gone past I will turn the inner eye to see its path. Where the fear has gone there will be nothing. Only I will remain. &amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hear no evil. See no evil. Speak no evil.</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-hear-no-evil-see-no-evil-speak-no-evil-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-hear-no-evil-see-no-evil-speak-no-evil-publish/</guid>
      <description>I had an epiphany tonight about something that just about everyone knows: the three monkeys. And I wanted to share it with you.
The three monkeys are accompanied by the words: &#34;See no evil. Hear no evil. Speak no evil.&#34; The funny thing is that one monkey is covering his eyes, one monkey is covering his ears, and one monkey is covering his mouth! Let&#39;s examine that for a second.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tooth of Knowledge (Lyrics)</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-the-tooth-of-knowledge-lyrics-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-the-tooth-of-knowledge-lyrics-publish/</guid>
      <description>This song is at least as old as 1973 and is originally from Italy (Giorgio Gaber - Dente della conoscenza). If you like finding patterns, making analogies and metaphors, and overall pondering, then examine the tooth of knowledge in the contexts of: science, religion, culture, society (etiquette, etc), and finally, the internet.
&amp;nbsp;
(note : &#39;SHHH&#39; is an inhaling sound)
‘TICK’ and then ‘SHHH’, ‘TICK’ and then ‘SHHH’, ‘TICK’ and then ‘SHHH’, ‘TICK’ and then ‘SHHH’, ‘TICK’ and then ‘SHHH’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Society&#39;s focus on knowledge</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-society-focus-on-knowledge-draft/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-society-focus-on-knowledge-draft/</guid>
      <description>Here is a thought with which I&#39;ve been wrestling for quite a while - the focus of society on knowledge and what it could be doing to us as people, human beings, and members of society, as well as to society itself. Knowledge is power - knowing more can only help you In the West (bounded to the east by Russia and to the west by the Americas), the focus has historically been on developing more knowledge, more science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matt Damon&#39;s Speech at the Save Our Schools Rally</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-matt-damons-speech-at-the-save-our-schools-rally-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-matt-damons-speech-at-the-save-our-schools-rally-publish/</guid>
      <description>I flew overnight from Vancouver to be with you today. I landed in New York a few hours ago and caught a flight down here because I needed to tell you all in person that I think you’re awesome. I was raised by a teacher. My mother is a professor of early childhood education. And from the time I went to kindergarten through my senior year in high school, I went to public schools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The world is shrinking: two videos</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-two-videos-a-change-in-the-world-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-two-videos-a-change-in-the-world-publish/</guid>
      <description>Those two videos have been brought to my attention within maybe two weeks of each other, and I hate thinking of random coincidences.. So here they are, together so I can find them again in several years. Playing for change: Stand by me Where the hell is Matt?
The first one fills my heart with a warm feeling - the song was recorded by all these people around the world simultaneously (or so they say, but it sure is well edited in any case).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>