<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>martial-arts on Seven steps</title>
    <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/categories/martial-arts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in martial-arts on Seven steps</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/trevoke&#34;&gt;Aldric Giacomoni&lt;/a&gt; 2017-2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.trevoke.net/categories/martial-arts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Shu ha ri and evolution of a skill</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-shu-ha-ri-and-evolution-of-a-skill-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-shu-ha-ri-and-evolution-of-a-skill-publish/</guid>
      <description>Shu Ha Ri comes from the world of Japanese Noh theater, and has been since attached to the world of martial arts and Agile development. Roughly, &#34;shu ha ri&#34; means &#34;learn / detach / transcend&#34;. The link has some words about that meaning. I&#39;d like to talk about my particular take on Shu Ha Ri, which came out of a parking-lot conversation with a martial arts teacher friend of mine:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Class</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-first-class-private/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-first-class-private/</guid>
      <description>The first class went really well.
My teaching tempo is still pretty good, though I did underestimate how much information I was giving the new students. Next time, I need to make sure I don&#39;t overwhelm them, and keep them to a smaller set of basics.
This feels right. I know it&#39;s what I&#39;m going to keep doing. Now I need to balance continued growth with proper teaching time. If I can do this twice a week, I&#39;ll have a good next step.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sparring</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-sparring-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-sparring-publish/</guid>
      <description>What Sparring Is Sparring is a playful and explorative interaction.
Sparring is an exercise, a drill. The Japanese use the word KUMITE - which basically means &#34;grouped hands&#34; or &#34;pair hands&#34;, &#34;joined hands&#34;, &#34;hands together&#34; (the Wikipedia article suggests &#34;grappling hands&#34;).
Sparring is a two-person free-form exercise wherein you get to examine scenarios involving combinations, footwork, distancing, rhythm, controlled power, and focus to improve yourself and your partner.

Combinations: you get to play first-hand with things you have learned and put them in an environment where there is no set response.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>School creed</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-school-creed-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-school-creed-publish/</guid>
      <description>In the dojo where I spent my formative years as a martial artist, there is a school creed. A quick search online has revealed that many schools have a similar creed. Every class says it as we begin, after bowing in, before calisthenics. I hear it and/or say it about three times per dojo night.
It&#39;s a simple creed, and clearly not unique. Here&#39;s what it says:
I intend to develop myself in a positive manner and avoid anything that would reduce my mental growth or physical health.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The schism in martial training paradigms</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-the-schism-in-martial-training-paradigms-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-the-schism-in-martial-training-paradigms-publish/</guid>
      <description>You&#39;re training wrong! No, YOU&#39;re training wrong!
A recent set of conversations have led me to examine the major difference in martial training. I&#39;m going to start by separating training in two categories, making an imperfect black-and-white model of the martial world:
 Traditional eastern training Jeet Kune Do-like training 
Now, let&#39;s start to talk about the PURPOSE of each, in a fairly roundabout way.
Let&#39;s talk about the traditional drill which has become sort of a standard: &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Punches and the lower back</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-punches-and-lower-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-punches-and-lower-back/</guid>
      <description>Sensei helped me figure out that my punches are all wrong, and the issue has been traced to lower back muscles. Thankfully, I&#39;ve got tons of subway time now, so I can practice standing. For those of you who don&#39;t study martial arts... That last sentence is not a joke.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nidan test</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-nidan-test-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-nidan-test-publish/</guid>
      <description>On February 28th, 2010, I took the test to become a second-degree black belt.
Here is a summary of what I had to do, besides the calisthenics:
 All my empty-hand forms, opposite side. There are eight of them. This meant that if the first step was with the left foot, I had to do it with the right foot. I suppose you could also call that &#39;mirror&#39;. The names are : seisan, seiuchin, naihanchi, wonsu, chinto, kusanku, sunsu, and sanchin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching kusanku to sankyu</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-teaching-kusanku-to-sankyu-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-teaching-kusanku-to-sankyu-publish/</guid>
      <description>Last night, after some kicking drills and sparring, sensei entrusted the adult class to me and told us to work on kusanku. The &#39;adult class&#39; yesterday consisted of three sankyu. I looked at the clock, rubbed my hands together and said &#34;Alright everyone, we have twenty-five minutes&#39; worth of kusanku. Let me know if you have questions or doubts.&#34;
When we had finished walking through it, I looked at the clock.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday night training</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-monday-night-training-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-monday-night-training-publish/</guid>
      <description>I received an email from sensei on Monday (sent to every student) - if you&#39;ll be here tonight, bring your fighting gear. Uh-oh. Her sensei was there and taught a few classes, including the adults. The entire class turned out to be pretty much a blur of drills. I&#39;ll be able to dredge them out of my body memory, I think. A drill about basics - chain two basics together, using shifting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why do I study martial arts?</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-why-do-i-study-martial-arts-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-why-do-i-study-martial-arts-publish/</guid>
      <description>I am watching Rocky III and IV (the only ones I really like), and the driving theme is the power of the human spirit. Rewatching it now, I see a lot of other ideas. They&#39;re not particularly hidden, but I never really noticed them before. This started to make me think about my choices.
My lasting decision to study martial arts was made in college, and I took a Physical Education class of self-defense taught by shifu Christopher Goedecke, who studies and teaches isshin kempo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tonight&#39;s training (good AGAIN!)</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-tonights-training-good-again-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-tonights-training-good-again-publish/</guid>
      <description>It was surprisingly good. I didn&#39;t feel very good tonight - slight headache, slight tingle in the throat. I wasn&#39;t going to stay for my class, just help teach and then go home, get tea, get sleep.. But only two other adults showed up and sensei was upstairs, so I started the class and took it easy on the calisthenics and the stretches. Those two adults are the two with the most issues of muscle contractions (as in, they have no idea what relaxing means).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another awesome training evening</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-another-awesome-training-evening-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-another-awesome-training-evening-publish/</guid>
      <description>So tonight, I went to train 35 minutes away from home, at the dojo where my sensei&#39;s sensei teaches. Warmups / stretches, kicking drills, calisthenics, sparring, then fighting drills. Sensei&#39;s sensei has a son who is now 48. Now -- I am fast by normal people&#39;s standards. This guy is really fast by my standards. He also has a really positive energy - very friendly eyes, a great disposition.. And he can dislocate your jaw before you can blink or think &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dojo tonight</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-dojo-tonight-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-dojo-tonight-publish/</guid>
      <description>I had a good time in the dojo tonight. Managed to bring a kid back from the verge of tears to feeling good and performing kata with solid focus and intent.. And then good sparring. Kid&#39;s 6, by the way. My class wasn&#39;t that good, though I got a compliment on my push-ups from sensei. Went through my kicks.. Then sparred..
I fleetingly get a grasp of efficient body movement, and then it disappears, and then I have to train a lot more to make it happen again, and then more again, etc etc, until I can make it happen effortlessly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spending energy uselessly</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-spending-energy-uselessly-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-spending-energy-uselessly-publish/</guid>
      <description>I live on an island. It only took me until last week (10 years and change) to take my dad&#39;s advice to go to the beach when I felt like it. So I did that, last week and today, and went swimming. Good for the muscles, good all-around body work. Great stretching. Different way of using the muscles.
Besides the fact that I could really only swim for 10-15 minutes before I was tired and a part of my arms started to ache (indicating, clearly, that I&#39;d been ignoring it), I noticed on my way home that even just 30 minutes at the beach drained me of energy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who follows who?</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-who-follows-who-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-who-follows-who-publish/</guid>
      <description>In the past couple of weeks, I&#39;d gotten to spar progressively harder with a blue belt who is twice my age, but has been in dojos where sparring and self-defense were more important than kata. As a result, I consider him somewhat dangerous to spar with.. And, well, I let myself get caught up. I stopped being the watcher..
I hid behind the excuse that I was just sparring as hard as he wanted to spar, and so it just escalated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaxing the upper body.. aka &#34;drop your shoulders&#34;</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-relaxing-the-upper-body-aka-drop-your-shoulders-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-relaxing-the-upper-body-aka-drop-your-shoulders-publish/</guid>
      <description>A friend of mine wrote about shoulder relaxation.. Apparently we both had the same mental block, but he solved it first - shoulder relaxation (and by extension, all relaxation) can be done up/down and ... forward/back!
At first I didn&#39;t think I had that issue, my western mind automatically went &#34;Nah, I don&#39;t have that issue, my shoulders are nice and straight!&#34; .. And then training kicked in and the answer came : &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>stances</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-stances-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-stances-publish/</guid>
      <description>Tonight we had training on stances. It came about more or less accidentally - proper stances are -hard- !! But I am now flexible enough hip-wise to get there.. Now to train my leg muscles, mostly the quads, to follow suit...</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nidan... ?</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-nidan-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-nidan-publish/</guid>
      <description>Well, sensei hinted last month that maybe I should start gearing up for a nidan test. I&#39;ve been getting used to being shodan, which maybe is a bad thing, but I haven&#39;t stopped looking for things I could do better. I&#39;m becoming more sensitive to the muscles in my back, and I think my shoulders are finally beginning to open up...
So, I have something like 5 months to prepare.. Or, you know, whenever it turns out sensei thinks I&#39;m ready.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More students testing</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-more-students-testing-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-more-students-testing-publish/</guid>
      <description>This week two more students tested. We have a new green belt and a new blue belt. They did pretty well, but I am completely amazed at how many excuses adults have. Their heads are full of them. Can&#39;t they just listen and say &#39;yes&#39; like they were taught when they were kids? Talking back is a privilege, not a right. Ooh.. That&#39;s good.. I&#39;ll reuse that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martial arts while sick</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-martial-arts-while-sick-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-martial-arts-while-sick-publish/</guid>
      <description>On Monday I went to the dojo as usual, though I&#39;d had a cold over the week-end and wasn&#39;t quite over it (I&#39;m still not over it now..). During form practice, I was constantly correcting myself - I guess that goes to show I need to practice a lot more, if I dedicate this much mindpower to each form.. :)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An old-school 6th dan</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-an-old-school-6th-dan-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-an-old-school-6th-dan-publish/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday evening a man who trained about as long as sensei came to train with us. Black obi, rather frayed to white. He&#39;d trained a long time under his uncle, and then ~15 years under sensei&#39;s sensei. He&#39;d taken a break for a while, so he was a bit out of shape, but his mindset, his attitude, his devotion were 100% into everything he did - an important lesson which I forget all too often.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kali sticks</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-kali-sticks-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-kali-sticks-publish/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday we had a small class, so we were able to each work on what we needed. I, hopefully, now have the full chatan yara no sai form, so I just need to work it..
We did some kali stick work. The yellow and blue belt had never seen those drills before so we started with a simple high-low-high, but we did try for a little bit the sinawali drills, specifically heaven, because that one&#39;s fun :) Kali sticks are very good to work follow-through, speed and flow, and god knows I need that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing for purple</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-testing-for-purple-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-testing-for-purple-publish/</guid>
      <description>Monday and yesterday, two blue belts were to test for purple. They went through their calisthenics and basics; I did not see their forms on Monday, but I did see them on Wednesday. They were bad enough sensei wanted to see them again, that much I understood, but not sure how bad until I saw them both.
Neither of them broke a sweat until fighting, not for the 100 jumping jacks, not for the 60 push-ups, not for the multiple kick combinations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solved my left shoulder pain?</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-solved-my-left-shoulder-pain-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-solved-my-left-shoulder-pain-publish/</guid>
      <description>Is it a worrying trend that I write mostly about pain in here? :)
Every once in a while, usually while doing a high block with my left arm, I&#39;d feel a pain in my left shoulder. It felt like a part was rolling over another one.. Muscle over bone, or something like that. It&#39;s not pleasant and is the kind of pain that stops your movement quite short and quite abruptly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hurt my mid-back...</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-hurt-my-mid-back-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-hurt-my-mid-back-publish/</guid>
      <description>I don&#39;t know how I did it, but at some point during my empty hand class, I hurt my back. Think of a line going horizontally across the middle of the back (under the shoulderblades), and you have it. I didn&#39;t stay for weapons past my bo class and went home. I was OK during my sword class, which means either I wasn&#39;t paying attention, or I wasn&#39;t using those muscles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Found the solar plexus yet?</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-found-the-solar-plexus-yet-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-found-the-solar-plexus-yet-publish/</guid>
      <description>We have a move in a form that requires holding a hand in front of the solar plexus. One of the kids was holding his hand a little low, so I mentioned it to him.. He start hitting his chest a few times with his hand, so I laugh. &#34;Think you got it?&#34; He does it a few more times and starts coughing. &#34;Ah, now you got it.&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So, you want to spar?</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-so-you-want-to-spar-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-so-you-want-to-spar-publish/</guid>
      <description>Sparring can be one of the many reasons one wants to join a martial arts school, sometimes even their only interest. Unless you join a school based on street defense, you may not do as much as you&#39;d like. Besides, the insurances and legality issues being what they are, usually you are limited to sparring gear which lets you mostly throw punches and kicks.
The teacher of a traditional school probably won&#39;t let you spar until after you get a belt or two, because you need to break in your body and the techniques you are learning -- besides, you don&#39;t have enough control to know when to stop your strikes, so if your opponent fails to block, you could hurt him quite a bit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Which martial arts school is right for you?</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-which-martial-arts-school-is-right-for-you-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-which-martial-arts-school-is-right-for-you-publish/</guid>
      <description>So, you&#39;ve decided to start taking a martial arts class. Good for you!
Why do you want to join? Is it to fight, to learn to defend yourself, to develop self-discipline, to learn kata (&#39;forms&#39;), for health reasons? All of the above?
For the purpose of this article (if nothing else), I will make a differentiation between a fighting style and a martial art. In a fighting style, you are learning to fight, and that is it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>