<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sparring on Seven steps</title>
    <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/tags/sparring/</link>
    <description>Recent content in sparring on Seven steps</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/trevoke&#34;&gt;Aldric Giacomoni&lt;/a&gt; 2017-2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.trevoke.net/tags/sparring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sparring</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-sparring-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-sparring-publish/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;What Sparring Is&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt; Sparring is a playful and explorative interaction.  Sparring is an exercise, a drill. The Japanese use the word KUMITE - which basically means &amp;#34;grouped hands&amp;#34; or &amp;#34;pair hands&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;joined hands&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;hands together&amp;#34; (the Wikipedia article suggests &amp;#34;grappling hands&amp;#34;).  Sparring is a two-person free-form exercise wherein you get to examine scenarios involving combinations, footwork, distancing, rhythm, controlled power, and focus to improve yourself and your partner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tonight&#39;s training (good AGAIN!)</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-tonights-training-good-again-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-tonights-training-good-again-publish/</guid>
      <description>It was surprisingly good. I didn&amp;#39;t feel very good tonight - slight headache, slight tingle in the throat. I wasn&amp;#39;t going to stay for my class, just help teach and then go home, get tea, get sleep.. But &amp;lt;!–more–&amp;gt;only two other adults showed up and sensei was upstairs, so I started the class and took it easy on the calisthenics and the stretches. Those two adults are the two with the most issues of muscle contractions (as in, they have no idea what relaxing means).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So, you want to spar?</title>
      <link>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-so-you-want-to-spar-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.trevoke.net/post/import-so-you-want-to-spar-publish/</guid>
      <description>Sparring can be one of the many reasons one wants to join a martial arts school, sometimes even their only interest. Unless you join a school based on street defense, you may not do as much as you&amp;#39;d like. Besides, the insurances and legality issues being what they are, usually you are limited to sparring gear which lets you mostly throw punches and kicks.  The teacher of a traditional school probably won&amp;#39;t let you spar until after you get a belt or two, because you need to break in your body and the techniques you are learning – besides, you don&amp;#39;t have enough control to know when to stop your strikes, so if your opponent fails to block, you could hurt him quite a bit.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>